Finding Aid for the Lloyd E. Cotsen Cuneiform Tablets Collection LSC.1883
UCLA Library Special Collections
- School text, letter exercise with envelope., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-29; 2 9/16" height x 1 3/4" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet with an inscribed envelope covering 75% of the tablet surface; Rectangular envelope fragment with tablet inside. Half of one face and side of the envelope fragment is missing. The existing edges at this loss are jagged and have a powdery texture. There are some incomplete cracks overall on the envelope fragment as well as some surface losses. There are some cuneiform impressions visible on one face. These impressions are flanked by surface losses in one corner and losses to the other corner so any other impression that may have existed in that area are gone. The tablet has losses in one corner and along an edge (where a portion of the envelope fragment is also gone). Only a portion of the tablet is visible (where the envelope has broken anwyway). The edges where there are losses also have a powdery texture. There are white concretions visible mostly on one side of the revealed portion of the tablet and on one edhe of the envelope fragment. (Drawer 2)
  This basic student exercise of writing a letter includes the envelope, which has a short inscription on it.
- School text, lexical exercise of types of boats., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-1C; Obverse 1. … 2. … boat 3. … boat 4. A raft 5. Ancestor-boat 6. A prow 7. Weapon boat 8. A boat with an awning 9. … boat 10. … Reverse 1. … boat 2. A fisherman's boat 3. …; 2 13/16" height x 1 7/8" width x 3/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectagular tablet with a number of complete and incomplete cracks. Many of these cracks, and the area around these cracks have been covered with an adhesive. There are losses along many of these cracks. There are losses at one corner and other minor surface losses. There are two rough gouges on one face --possibly these were made while the clay was still wet, based on the patina. One gouge runs across half of the face, the other gouge is at one edge. There are white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 3)
  This student vocabular exercise is taken from the Old Babylonian Ura 1 list of wooden objects. This list focuses on types of boats.
- School text, sign exercise from unknown Syllabary., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-IV-7; (Syllabary--no translation); 2 7/8" height x 1 9/16" width x 1/2" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet fragment with losses at one edge. This edge is jagged due to these losses. There is a gouge mark on one face that appears to have been made with a modern tool. There is an incomplete crack at one corner. There are some white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 4)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing simple signs.
- School text, administrative exercise and lexical exercise of personal names., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 20; 2 1/2" height x 1 3/4" width x 5/8" depth, red baked rectangular single column tablet with transposed writing on the reverse; Rectangular tablet fragment. There is a loss at one corner, another edge is lost, and there are surface losses from spalling near the edge that has been lost. there are other minor surface losses and chips overall. There are a number of incomplete cracks throughout. A coating appears to have been applied on the surface of the fragment. (Drawer 5)
  This student exercise has an administrative exercise on the obverse and a short section of Akkadian personal names transposed on the reverse
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names beginning with "mu"., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 146; 1. 'The assembler'; 2. 'Benefactress'; 3. 'The seller'; 4. 'The shelterer'; 5. 'The multitude'; 6. 'The intelligent one'; 3 7/16" height x 3" width x 3/4" depth, red baked square single column tablet joined from fragments; An almost square tablet broken into two pieces and repaired. The repair is relatively well done. Adhesive is confined to the repair area. The tablet appears well fired. (Drawer 6)
  This basic student exercise is practice writing personal names. This text is nearly identical to 96262.
- School text, sign exercise from Proto-diri., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-3; (Too broken to reconstruct); 2 3/8" height x 2" width x 1 1/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet of grey-brown clay that has some losses at three of its corners. There are some groove marks and depressions on the edges of the tablet. While most of these marks seem to be minor scratches or losses to the surface, a few of the marks on the thickest edge were possibly made by an implement. Possibly, these marks were made when the clay was wet, though it is difficult to tell. There is a black patina with a little sheen on many of the raised areas of the surface; possibly this is a result of handling or wear. (Drawer 1)
  This tablet contains a beginner student's practice writing compound signs. The text has been overwritten at least once making it difficult to reconstruct the contents of the tablet.
- School text, lexical exercise of wooden objects and grammatical exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-35a; (Too broken to reconstruct); 2 3/4" height x 1 5/8" width x 3/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet with severely effaced surfaces and transposed writing on the reverse; Rectangular tablet with some minor losses to the edges and three of the corners. There is one incomplete crack running from one edge to about 1 1/2" across one face. The surface of the tablet has several rough patches of varying tan and brown colors. It is unclear if this was part of the makeup of the tablet before it was dried, or if these are deposits or dirt. There are a few small white concretions visible throughout. (Drawer 2)
  This student tablet contains a lexical exercise on the obverse and a grammatical exercise transposed on the reverse.
- School text, mathematical exercise of square roots., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-31; 2 3/4" height x 1 3/4" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet fragment that has broken into two pieces. The two pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. The break appears to be along a large portion of the surface (versus a clean break through the tablet) There is adhesive visible along the break on one of the faces. There is a small surface loss on this same face, just above the top of the break that has been reattached with adhesive. Along the edges with losses, it looks like there were two "layers" of clay used to form the tablet and that the "top" layer has been lost. (Drawer 3)
  This text is a student's practice of a table of square roots.
- School text, literary exercise from The Goose and the Raven., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 44554; 4 1/4" height x 2 1/4" width x 1 1/16" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet; Both faces of the tablet have several areas of loss that are filled with a substance colored white; this color distinguishes the fills from the original clay. One face has an incomplete crack running from a corner fill diagonally across to a second fill. That same face has another incomplete crack running most of the length of one edge. The opposite face has a few small, incomplete cracks, but this face has larger areas of fill. The color of the clay on the tablet varies greatly, from a deep orange-red to a light tan. (Drawer 4)
  This advanced student exercise contains part of a Sumerian fable.
- School text, sign exercise from Syllable Alphabet A., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-18; (Syllabary--no translation); 3 1/8" diameter x 13/16" depth, lentil; Disc-shaped tablet with inscription on one face only. It appears to have been compressed while the clay was still wet, leaving it somewhat misshapen. The tablet broke approximately in half diagonally; the two pieces were reattached with clear adhesive. Adhesive is visible on the surface of both faces, but moreso on the uninscribed face. The inscribed face has an area of spalling adjacent to the repaired break. There are two small, chipped losses at one edge, and both have white material (stone?) within them. The uninscribed face has a diagonal gouge at one edge that appears to be caused by a strike from a modern tool. There is a spalled loss at one end of the repaired break. About half of this face has several shallow, pitted losses. Many of these pitted spots have white material (stone?) within them. (Drawer 5)
  This elementary exercise in sign and sound formation allowed the new scribe to practice forming the basic signs: U, BAR and LA2.
- School text, lexical exercise from bilingual kagal = abullu., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 148; 3" height x 2 3/8" width x 3/4" depth, baked rectangular single column tablet; Tablet fragment. The tablet has breaks and losses to every corner and edge. There are shallow, vertical cracking on both faces. The surface appears to have been coated.
  This elementary student exercise is practice writing agricultural terminology.
- School text, legal exercise of a sale contract., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-24e; 4 7/8" height x 2 1/8" width x 7/8" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has been broken into two pieces. These pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. The adhesive is visible on the surface around the break in some areas. On one face is a long, incomplete crack running from one corner with a loss to the center, with smaller incomplete cracks branching out in some spots. On the other face, there is another incomplete crack that runs from one corner to a point on the break. Adhesive has also been applied to these cracks and the surface around the cracks. There is a large loss along the break near one edge; a large chunk is missing. There are smaller losses along the rest of the break creating gaps and crevices. It is possible that a portion of the break on one face has been filled. On this same face, there is another loss to the surface that is partially covered with adhesive and possibly the remains of a fill. Along the edge with the large loss, there are four pit-like losses, possibly made by an implement. There are spots and lines of white-grey concretions visible overall. (Drawer 1)
  This tablet contains a student's exercise in writing a contract for the sale of land, a task with which every scribe needed to be proficient.
- School text, literary exercise from The Song of the Hoe., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-25; 2 5/8" height x 2 1/4" width x 1" depth, baked red rectangular single column tablet; Square tablet fragment of red-brown clay. One of the edges has grooves that are possibly marks made by an implement used to break the fragment from another piece of tablet. There is a small loss on one corner and another loss on the surface of one edge, possibly from spalling. There is a white substance covering some areas of the surface throughout. (Drawer 2)
  This popular literary piece was part of the Decad, a standard collection of literary works mastered by advanced scribes. This excerpt covers lines 27-43 of the 108 line song.
- School text, mathematical exercise for volume calculations., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-36; 3 7/8" height x 2 1/8" width x 3/4" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Rectangular tablet with a noticeably deep, incomplete crack running through the surface of one face. Some adhesive has been applied along some points of the crack as well as on the surface around these points. There are a few other incomplete cracks on the same face. There is one complete crack near one edge. On the other face, there are some losses to the surface in two of the corners and two of the edges. Adhesive has been applied to those areas with losses in the corners. There are a few incomplete cracks in one of the corners with losses. The central portion of each face has a dark black patina that has some sheen. This sheen could possibly be from wear or could be a coating. (Drawer 3)
  These are a student's word problems for calculating volumes of soil for canal digging. Canals had to be redug reguarly in ancient Mesopotamia, so these types of math problems were very useful for the scribe.
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1b; 3 7/8" height x 2 1/16" width x 1" depth, rectangular single column tablet; Tablet with one corner broken off and partially lost. The portion of the corner that was not lost has been reattached with clear adhesive. The adhesive is partially visible on one face. The opposite face has a gouge at one side. This same face has dark black discoloration, possibly charring. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is from Shamash-bel-.. to Inashdu, concerning a field.
- School text, sign exercise from Proto-Lu., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-20; 1. Temple administrator 2. Associate temple administrator 3. Governor; 2 13/16" diameter x 11/16" depth, lentil; Disc-shaped tablet that is only inscribed on one face. There are two minor losses at one edge of the tablet. The uninscribed face has a chip near one edge with a small pit within it. Across from that there is a gouge. About 2/3 of the uninscribed face is partially spalled. (Drawer 5)
- School text, literary exercise from Lugal-e and scribal dialogues., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 91; 4" height x 2 1/2" width x 3/4" depth, red baked rectangular single column tablet; The tablet seems stable. One corner is broken and lost. Some hairline cracks along the loss. There is no evidence of adhesive, but the surface appears to have been coated. (Drawer 6)
  This advanced student exercise is a literary excerpt from Lugal-e (lines 100- 109). The reverse contains a dialogue between two scribes.
- School text, lexical exercise of personal names and a drawing exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-I-11; (Too fragmentary to translate); 2 3/4" diameter x 7/8" depth, lentil with surface damage; Lenticular tablet with a third of the flat face (the inscribed face) scraped off, probably while the clay was still wet. This same face is partially coated. There is a small loss on this same face that looks to have been reattached with adhesive. There is more scraping on the domed face at the edge near the drawing of a face, also most likely scraped while the clay was still wet. On this same side, there are also some small gouge marks near the center of the tablet. There are a few white concretions visible on the surface overall. (Drawer 1)
  This tablet contains a drawing of a face on the reverse. The obverse is too illegible to reconstruct.
- School text, administrative exercise., Ur III Period (c. 2100-2000 BCE); SC-I-21; Obverse Column 1 1. 24,130 1/2 liters of semolina, 2. 13,411 liters of barley, 3. loaned grains; 4. 4,877 liters of barley, 5. 567 liters of emmer, 6. 85 liters of wheat, 7. grain credits in the carried over debits; 8. new loaned grains; 9. 39,407 1/2 liters of flour, 10. 42,475 1/3 liters of barley, 11. 580 liters of reaped barley, 12. 570 1/2 liters of wheat, 13. loaned grains in the center of the entrusted house; 14. 23,727 liters of barley, 15. 3,010 liters of emmer, 16. carried over debits of the account done; 17. n+1,170 1/2 liters of barley, 18. … (The remaining lines are missing) Column 2 1. 12,000+ liters of … 2. offerings … 3. 2,760+ liters of … 4. … 5. 5 fleece-less sheep, 6. 34 female kids, 7. 24 minas and 10 shekels of gold, 8. sealed by Lugal-nig-lagare, 9. son of 'servant of temple of Eridu'; 10. 16,010 liters of flour, 11. 1,120 liters of barley, 12. new loaned grains; 13. 147 liters of flour, 14. 110,900 2/3 liters of barley, 15. 1,680 liters of flour, 16. carried over debits of the account done; 17. grains credited to the carried over debits; 18. its head … 19. barley … (The remaining lines are missing) Reverse Column 1 (The first two lines are missing) 3'. The middle of the basket. The year the western wall was built; 4'. 8,950 liters of flour, 5'. 13, 140 liters of reaped barley, 6'. 6,720 liters of loaned grain, 7'. sealed by He fills the palace; 8'. 46,410 liters of flour, 9'. 6,018+ liters of barley, 10'. carried over debits of the account done …; 11'. 3,000+ liters of reaped barley, 12'. sealed by Gududu; Column 2 1. The year Shu-Suen, king of Ur, built a grand stele for Enlil and Ninlil. 2. A copy sealed in the school by … (Drawer 2)
  This practice administrative text contains quantities of cereals. This text is dated to king Shu-Suen's 5th and 6th regnal years (c. 2032-2033 BCE).
- School text, letter exercise for royal correspondence., Ur III- Old Babylonian Period (c. 2100-1600 BCE); SC-II-3; 3 1/2" height x 2 1/4" width x 1 1/16" depth, rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; The tablet has broken along one long side, and two parts of the break at diagonally opposite corners have been lost. The broken portion that was not lost was reattached, but small areas of loss along the reattached break are visible on both faces. Some spalling has occurred at the corners near both lost corners. (Drawer 3)
  A practice letter from Aba-indasa to king Shulgi. Shulgi reigned from 2094- 2047 BCE.
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1e; 3 5/16" height x 2" width x 1 1/4", rectangular single column tablet with worn surfaces; Tablet with one corner broken and lost. There is clear adhesive visible within the break. One face has a deep but incomplete crack in the corner opposite the broken corner. A second crack (less deep) comes from the side and intersects the first crack. Spots of clear adhesive are on the surface covering portions of both cracks. One triangular-shaped piece has been lost along the deep crack. The opposite face has a gouge near one corner. The large corner break/loss described above is visible but less severe on this face. Another corner has spalling, but the damage appears old, as it has the same patina as the rest of the tablet. There are scattered white particles on both faces. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is from Ku-Nanna to Suen-bel-apli.
- School text, administrative exercise., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 6; 3 1/4" height x 1 7/8" width x 1 1/16" depth, red baked rectangular single column tablet; Fragment of a rectangular tablet. One long side has an area of spalling and two gouges. All of this damage has the same patina as the rest of the fragment, so it is not recent. A small white sticker with "2" written in blue ink was adhered to the side, between the area of spalling and the gouges. This sticker was removed at the time of condition reporting. One face has three small areas of light scraping near the unbroken corner. These areas have a lighter patina than the clay around them and may have been made by a modern tool strike. The opposite face has an area of spalling on part of one edge, following the contour of the break. (Drawer 5)
  This is a basic student exercise in drafting administrative documents. Administrative texts are the most prevalent and popular type of ancient Mesopotamian text, so the scribe need ample practice to master this genre.
- School text, legal exercise for a loan contract., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 151; 3 1/4" height x 1 7/8" width x 3/4" depth, red baked rectangular single column tablet with the reverse uninscribed; An almost complete tablet; there are losses to three corners. Only one face has been inscribed, the other is smooth. The piece appears relatively well fired. The surface may be coated. (Drawer 6)
  This tablet contains a student's exercise in writing a contract for a loan of barley.
- School text, lexical exercise of bird names., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); 31718.2; 1. The esig bird 2. The shulu bird 3. The gakad bird; 2 3/4" diameter x 3/8" depth, lentil; A small lenticular tablet of light yellow-baff clay. The tablet has multiple losses and is actively crumbling and powdery. There are three main areas of loss along the edge. The uninscribed face has small hairline cracks throughout. The incised face has areas of dark concretion scattered overall. (Drawer 1)
- School text, mathematical exercise of surveying., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-26; 1 5/8" height x 1 5/8" width x 7/8" depth, square tablet; Square tablet of grey-tan clay with a few minor losses to the surface. The surface has a few rough patches and areas where the surface is blackened. There are several white concretions visible overall. (Drawer 2)
  This tablet contains a student's drawing of a plan of a rectangular plot of land. The dimensions are given on reverse.
- School text, letter exercise., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-II-8; 2 1/8" height x 1 3/4" width x 9/16" depth, baked square single column tablet; The tablet has lost a small portion of one corner. The damage appears to be ancient, as it has the same patina as the rest of the tablet. (Drawer 3)
  This student exercise is practice in drafting a letter using the appropriate format and techniques.
- School text, letter exercise with envelope fragment., Old Babylonian Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); SC-III-1i; 3 5/8" height x 1 15/16" width x 1 1/2" depth, rectangular single column tablet; This rectangular tablet has a fragment of envelop that has dried to one face. The opposite face appears to have been smashed/compressed toward center while the clay was still wet. About half of the surface of the envelop fragment has spalled. There ar a few scattered white spots near the edge on this face. The opposite face is misshapen from being compressed while the clay was wet. One portion of this compressed area has a scrape or gouge, possibly from a modern tool. At one edge of this face there are two areas of spalling that continue onto the short side. Both faces have blackened areas much darker than the rest of the clay. These may be scorch marks. (Drawer 4)
  This student practice letter is from Ur-Zababa, who writes to Silli-Shamash about barley rations.
- School text, administrative exercise of ration lists., Old Babylonian - Period (c. 1900-1600 BCE); PARS 33; 4 1/2" height x 1 7/8" width x 1" depth, red baked rectangular single column tablet joined from fragments; Rectangular tablet that has broken into two pieces. These two pieces have been reattached with an adhesive. There are some losses along the break, particularly along the break on the uninscribed face. On this same face, there are shallow craters. It is unclear whether these were made when the clay was wet or after the tablet was fired. There is also some spalling and some thin crevices that are possibly from folds in the clay when it was still wet, or from losses. There is an incomplete hairline crack near one edge on this face. There are some other minor surface chips and scratches overall. A coating has been applied to the surface of the tablet overall. (Drawer 5)
  This basic student practice text contains lists of rations distributed to workers as payment.